Sandra Bagnall collection on Millicent Hamburger LSC.2175
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sandra Bagnall collection on Millicent Hamburger
1928-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bagnall, Sandra
Mayes, Elaine
LSC.2175
14.2 linear feet (15 document boxes; 3 record cartons; 4 shoeboxes; 3 flat boxes; 3 oversize flat boxes)
Millicent Hamburger was a modern dance teacher who taught at Acalanes High School, in the Bay Area town of Lafayette, California, for three decades. This collection contains production files, correspondence, photographs, audiovisual recordings, and ephemera generated or collected from Hamburger's archive by one of her former students, Sandra Bagnall, during the creation of the documentary film, When I Dance. Also included are Hamburger's personal papers and books from her library on dance.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital and audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Bagnall, 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9979929393606533
Biography/History
Millicent Hamburger (born 1903) was raised in New York, graduated from Smith College and received her M.A. in English from Columbia University. While at Columbia, she began studying with Ethel Mandell, a student of the Isadora Duncan School, and later accepted a teaching position in dance at the settlement houses in New York City. In 1941, Hamburger relocated to Lafayette, California (in the Bay Area), where she taught English and directed the modern dance group at Acalanes High School for three decades. The Acalanes Dance Group gave two performances a year, in the winter and spring, and was well- loved by generations of Acalanes dancers. Retiring and returning to New York in 1970, she nonetheless returned annually to Lafayette for dance reunions with her former students. Hamburger passed away in Orient, New York on 1 June 2004.
Sandra Humble Bagnall was a student of Millicent Hamburger and a member of the Acalanes Dance Group. Her documentary film about these experiences, When I Dance, was completed in 2002.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials gathered by Sandra Bagnall during the production of her film When I Dance, about the modern dance program at Acalanes High School and its director, Millicent Hamburger. Materials include production files; correspondence; photographic prints, negatives, and slides; audio and moving image recordings of Acalanes performances, dancers, class reunions, and interviews; and ephemera such as concert posters and programs for Acalanes performances. Many of the photographs have been taken by Elaine Mayes. Also included are personal papers and books from the library of Millicent Hamburger.
Organization and Arrangement
Collection has been organized into the following series:
Series 1. When I Dance production files
Subseries 1.1. Process and treatments
Subseries 1.2. Recording logs
Subseries 1.3. Funding and legal documents
Subseries 1.4. Screenings and press
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Class material
Series 4. Photographs
Series 5. Recordings
Modern dance -- United States.; Dance teachers -- United States.; Hamburger, Millicent
- Series 1. When I Dance production files, 1986-2004
  Scope and Content
  This series contains the production files for When I Dance, which include notes, outlines, recording logs, inventories, contact information, legal documents, grant information, funding research and proposals, and screening material for the film.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Subseries 1.1. Process and treatments, 1986-2004
    - Scenarios & concept outline, circa 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Structure, circa 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Treatment I, 2000 July-August (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Treatment and performance changes, 2000 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rough cut changes- comments by Elaine, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Changes, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sandra's process diary, circa 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sandra notes, circa 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Script & narration, circa 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Script notes & research, circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Conversations with consultants, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Quotations research, circa 1990-2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Travel journal, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Credits, circa 2003 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Dancer contacts and performance information, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Sandra personal materials, 1986-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 1.2. Recording logs, 1998-2002
    This subseries contains logs and notes for the recorded material used in When I Dance. This material includes audio and video interviews, footage of dance reunions, and original footage of performances at Alcanes. Many of the referenced items are film and magnetic tape recordings that have been transferred to the Beta format. While the Beta recordings are not present in this collection, the original recordings, as well as later VHS transfers, are represented in Series 5.
    Original folder titles have been maintained.
    - 22 boxes, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alden- 1990 class selects, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Betty conversations with dancers/ Elaine 1990 class, circa 1999-2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Betty's VHS logs & notes (Elaine transfers), 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Conversation (1990)-A.R./ Millicent, Betty, Sandy, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Conversations with Millicent & Sandra/ Elaine 1998 & 1999, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - RC- Millicent conversations, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Tape interview with Millicent, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dance techniques and motions, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - DAT tape notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Dave Karp- 1998 selects, circa 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Elaine's conversations with dancers, Beta 12 & 14, circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Elaine's mystery logs, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ending, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Entry- classes- rough cut, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Film, MC, video, CD- backup, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Log of Paintings- Beta 19, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Motion control notes, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Performance logs for Alcanes footage, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - When I Dance- photo and word selects, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1.3. Funding and legal documents, 1998-2004
    SUBSERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - Transfer of rights to Millicent's archive, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Release forms from participants, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Grant information and proposal, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Film Arts Foundation, 1999-2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lafayette Arts & Science Foundation- Millicent Hamburger Fund, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Contributions/ notes of thanks, circa 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Progress report to contributors, 2000 March 16 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - When I Dance order forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Includes 1 zip disk.
      Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    - When I Dance release announcement, circa 2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1.4. Screenings and press, 2003-2004
    - Biographies for press kit, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Screenings and festival information, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Correspondence, 1989-2009
  This series contains correspondence between Sandra Bagnall, Elaine Mayes, and members of the Acalanes High School dance group, regarding the production of When I Dance. Also included is correspondence between Sandra Bagnall and Millicent Hamburger, and between Millicent Hamburger and the members of her dance group (including Sandra Bagnall).
  - Sandra and Millicent, 1980s-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Sandra and Elaine Mayes, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sandra and dancers, 1998-2009 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Sandra and Betsy Pembroke, written on the back of a shipping package, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Millicent and dancers, 1989-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 3. Class material, 1928-2000; 1940-1970
  This series contains original material from the Acalanes High School dance classes. This material was used for research purposes by Sandra Bagnall and includes student essays, poetry, and dance notations; concert programs and posters; Millicent Hamburger's writings; scrapbooks; and books on dance and Isadora Duncan, from Millicent Hamburger's library.
  - Student poetry, 1955-1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Class papers, circa 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Student notations for "Gypsy Smetana" production, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Student notations for "Job" production, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Notes, cards and letters for "Juggler of Notre Dame", 1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Millicent writing, 1942-1999 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Concert programs, 1940-1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Concert programs, 1950-1959 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - Concert programs, 1960-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Concert posters, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks, 1943-1958 (Box 6, Folder 3, Box 7, Box 8)
    Includes 3 full and 2 empty scrapbooks. Full scrapbooks contain photographs, notes, clippings, and ephemera for Acalanes dance productions from the years 1943-1958.
  - Scrapbooks - class reunions, 1993-1999 (Box 25)
  - Yearbooks - Acalanes Union High School, 1950-1952 (Box 26, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook - Ethel Mandell studio and students, 1932-1958 (Box 27)
    Primarily photos but also includes some programs and Mandell's writings about teaching the Isadora Duncan method of dance.
  - Books from the library of Millicent Hamburger, 1928-2000 (Box 28)
    Books are mainly autobiographies and biographies of Isadora Duncan. Also included are materials on dance instruction and an exhibition catalog for an Erika Giovanna Klien retrospective from 1989.
- Series 4. Photographs, 1920s-1994
  This series contains photographic negatives, contact sheets, and prints of Alcanes dance productions and student dancers, partly taken by Elaine Mayes. Also included are early photographs of Millicent Hamburger. Many of these images are numbered and were reprinted or resized by Sandra Bagnall for her work on her documentary, and some appeared in a 1969 photo-essay on Millicent Hamburger, also titled When I Dance. Many of the photographic prints were in Millicent Hamburger's files as of April 1999; they and their rights were legally transferred to Sandra Bagnall in 2003.
  - Negatives (Box 9, Box 10)
    Two boxes containing the source negatives for many of the print images in this series.
  - Christmas Flower (I), 1952 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Christmas Flower (II), 1956 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Down in the Valley, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dry Bones, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - The First Christmas Tree (I), 1954 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - The First Christmas Tree, 1960 December (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The First Christmas Tree/ Little Match Girl, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Joan of Arc, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Juggler of Notre Dame, 1955 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Little Match Girl (III), 1963 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Orpheus, 1952 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Pied Piper, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Pied Piper (Becki Chamberlain and Mary Hoole), 1964 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Salem Incident, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Salem Incident (II), 1967 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Scrooge I (Babs Springston), 1951 December 18 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Scrooge II (Carolyn Scalinetti), 1958 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Slavonic Dances, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Sleeping Beauty/ Carnevale, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Spirituals- Early California, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Who Am I? (Kate Young), 1957 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Barbara Lusebrink, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chrissie, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Clarice, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Diane Robertson, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Fausta Segrè, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Jeannie Golbraith/ Sally Freedman, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Karen Daniels, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Nancy Miller, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Class of 1970 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Ethel's Angels and settlement houses, circa 1930 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Millicent's old photographs, 1930-1950 (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
  - Calendar of dancers, 1994 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Stuyvesant House (removed from scrapbook), 1929 and undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Contact sheets and negatives (Elaine Mayes), 1960s (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Publicity glossies, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Sizing and proof sheets, undated (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
  - When I Dance book slides, 1982-1983 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Numbered photographs, 1920s-1970 (Box 15, Folder 2-5)
    These photographs have been numbered and labeled by Sandra Bagnall for use in her film. They include duplicates of photographs in previous folders, as well as original photographs ranging from the time of Millicent's instruction under Ethel Mandell, in the 1920s, to her own dance classes in 1970.
  - Unsorted negatives, 1940s-1970 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Unsorted contact sheets, 1940s-1970 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Unsorted photographs, 1940s-1970 (Box 16, Folder 1-8)
    These photographs originate in folders titled "miscellaneous", "unsorted", and "extras". They include much of the content in previous folders, though there is also some original material.
  - Mounted and oversize photographs, 1940s-1970 (Box 17, Box 18)
- Series 5. Recordings, 1940-2003
  This series contains recordings of Acalanes student dance productions, footage of the annual reunions attended by former Acalanes dancers, and material generated by Sandra Bagnall during the production of When I Dance, which includes interviews, video transfers, and finished masters of the film. Also included are audio recordings of a conversation with Millicent Bagnall and of the music used in the Acalanes dance performances.
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Acalanes dance performances and student dancers, 1940-1986 (Box 19, Box 20, Box 22)
    These film recordings originate in Millicent Hamburger's archive, and include footage of student dancers and of the following productions: Down in the Valley (1955), Joan of Arc (1951), Job (1958), Masquerade Suite (1949), The Salem Incident (1956), Symphonic Variations by Caesar Frank (1949), and Who Am I? (1957). Also included is footage of Millicent Hamburger in the Acalanes cafeteria in 1986.
    13 [8mm] and 38 [16mm] film reels
    RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of moving image material requires production of viewing copies.
  - Dance reunions, 1988-2001 (Box 21)
    Footage of the annual dance reunions attended by former Acalanes dance group members.
    34 VHS-C and 4 Hi8 cassettes
  - When I Dance video transfers, interviews, finished masters and DVD, [circa 1990]-2003 (Box 19, Box 22, Box 23)
    These boxes contain the VHS transfers for recordings of original dance footage from Acalanes and dance reunions (above), and interviews and conversations recorded by Sandra Bagnall in 1999. Many of the VHS cassettes correspond to previous transfers in Beta format, and are labeled as such. For more information on their contents, please refer to the logs in Subseries 1.2. Also included are the finished masters for When I Dance, and a DVD copy.
    67 VHS cassettes
  - Conversation with Millicent Hamburger, 1999 (Box 24)
    3 Digital Audio Tapes (DAT)
    RESTRICTED ACCESS: Use of audio material requires production of listening copies.
  - Music from performances, undated (Box 24)
    Includes: Ave Maria (Schubert), "Bartok", Blue Danube, Christmas Concerto (Corelli), Christmas Flower, Contra Dances (Beethoven), Down in the Valley, Gold and Silver, Hansel and Gretel, Joan of Arc, Liebesleider (Brahms), Little Match Girl, Negro Spirituals, Old Friends, Polonaise (Chopin), Salem Incident, Scrooge, Symphony, Voices, Waltz (Strauss), and Who Am I?
    10 compact audio cassettes
  - CD 16- Henrietta's Wedding/ Songs of African Veldt, undated (Box 24)
    1 CD